Finding Aid for Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing records, 1976-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing records 1976-2012
Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing.
2013060 Bimu 2
Established in 1976 by the University of Michigan College of Literature, Science and the Arts, the Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing (originally the English Composition Board) administers the writing program of the College and provides writing courses and assistance for students of the University from freshman year through graduate school. Collection contains administrative files covering all aspects of the Center's history as well as printed material and publications.
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received in March 2013 (donor no. 8136 ) through George Cooper.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 5-7
Science and the Arts (LS&A), the English Composition Board (ECB) was created. The ECB was charged with developing a plan for instruction that would improve the literacy of LS&A students. In 1978 the ECB began a multi-level, cross-curricular writing program, one of the first of its kind in universities around the country.
The ECB administered the writing program for the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, provided remediation and tutoring for those students that required it, ran the first year writing program, conducted writing workshops, offered upper-level courses in students' field of concentration to satisfy further graduation requirements ("Writing across the curriculum"), and conducted outreach workshops with area schools. One of its greatest responsibilities has been to evaluate incoming students' writing ability and assigning them to the appropriate writing course. The method for assessing the writing has changed over the last three decades, from essays written during freshman orientation to a portfolio of students' existing work from high-school to directed self-placement, the method currently used.
In 1998 the English Composition Board became the Gayle Morris Sweetland Writing Center in honor of Gayle Sweetland, founder and owner of U. Magazine. When the Sweetland Center moved from Angell Hall to newer facilities in North Quad in 2010, it became the Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing. The faculty of Sweetland work one-on-one with students in Writing Workshop and teach writing courses for students from their first year through graduate school. Additionally Sweetland offers peer tutoring, helps students navigate the University's writing requirements, and conducts research on ways to improve and innovate its programs and courses and contribute to national conversations about writing. Those interested in learning more about what Sweetland does may consult its website at http://www.lsa.umich.edu/sweetland/ (accessed May 2013).
The Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing collection is divided into four series: Administration, Publications and Printed Works, Audiovisual, and English Composition Board Writing Samples.
Subjects:
Gayle Morris Sweetland Center for Writing.; College prose--Evaluation.; English language--Composition and exercises--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan.; English language--Rhetoric.; English language--Rhetoric--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. English Composition Board.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Administration
  The Administration series (1976-2012, 3.2 linear feet) is further divided into two subseries, Core Administrative Files, and Topical Files. The Core Administrative Files subseries documents the day-to-day activities of the Center as well as its governance over its history. The subseries includes executive committee minutes, memos to faculty, annual reports, long-range plans, and several self and external evaluations of the ECB and Sweetland Center for Writing. The Topical files are arranged alphabetically and contain material about programs sponsored by the center, the research it has conducted, its liaisons with and involvement with other groups on campus and throughout Michigan, and its day-to-day activities.
  - Core Administrative Files
    - Annual and Year-End Reports
      - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 1)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 1)
      - Director's Year-End Reports 1983-2003 (Box 1)
    - Committees and Governance
      - Associate Directors' Meetings (Box 1)
        - 1990-1993 (Box 1)
        - 1993-1995 (Box 1)
        - 1995-1997 (Box 1)
      - Associate Directors' Retreats
        - 1993 (Box 1)
        - 1994 (Box 1)
        - 1995 (Box 1)
        - 1996 (Box 1)
      - Consulting Committee 1978 (Box 1)
      - ECB and LS&A Curriculum Committee 1981-1986 (Box 1)
      - Executive Committee
        - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
        - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
        - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
        - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
        - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
        - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
      - Policy Committee
        - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
        - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
        - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
        - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
        - 1988-1989 (Box 1)
      - Technology Committee 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence re: Writing Program 1994-1995 (Box 1)
      - ECB/LS&A Memos 1994-1995 (Box 1)
      - Memos re: Junior/Senior Writing 1994 (Box 1)
      - Memos re: Merit Pay 1993-1994 (Box 1)
      - Memos to ECB Faculty
        - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
        - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
        - 1997-1998 (Box 1)
        - 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Department Meetings
      - 1995-1997 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Meetings
      - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
      - 1993-1996 (Box 2)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Funding and Budgets
      - Budgets 1994-2002 (Box 2)
      - Budget Requests, FY 2004 (Box 2)
      - Requests for Funding 1985-1993 (Box 2)
    - Historical and Founding Documents
      - English Composition Board History (Box 2)
      - ECB Conference Proceedings, 12 May 1978 (Box 2)
      - ECB Reorganization 1984-1986 (Box 2)
      - ECB Reorganization Correspondence 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Staff Reorganization Plan 1993 (Box 2)
      - ECB/English Department Consolidation 1996-1997 (Box 2)
      - Proposed Writing Center 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Organization and Description
      - ECB Staffing and Organizational Charts 1988-2000 (Box 2)
      - ECB Thoughts on Role and Function, Fall 1988 (Box 2)
    - Planning
      - Long Range Plans
        - Winter 2000 (Box 2)
        - May 2003 (Box 2)
        - 2004 (Box 2)
    - Policies
      - ECB Position Statement on Sexism in Language undated (Box 2)
      - Policies on Staff Support 1983 (Box 2)
      - Policies Regarding Faculty Evaluation, ECB, 1985-89 (Box 2)
    - Reviews
      - Evaluation
        - Review Committee on the English Composition Board 1983-1984 (Box 2)
        - Reactions to 1984 External Review, 1984 (Box 2)
      - Self-Study
        - ECB Self Study 1983 (Box 2)
        - Chairman Commentary on ECB Self-Study 1984 (Box 2)
        - ECB Self Study August 1995 (Box 2)
      - Report to the College Executive Committee on Activities of the English Composition Board since July 1 1985 March 19 86 (Box 2)
      - Report of the Committee to Review Selected Instructional Support Units, 1982-83 (Box 2)
      - Report on Composition/ECB Writing Program December 1988 (Box 2)
      - Review, Writing in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts November 1995 (Box 2)
      - "This Teaching Works: The English Composition Board at the University of Michigan," August 1981 (Box 2)
    - Staff Meetings
      - 1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980 (Box 2)
      - 1981 (Box 2)
      - 1989-1993 (Box 2)
      - 1993-1995 (Box 2)
      - 1995 (Box 2)
  - Topical Files
    - Articles about ECB/Sweetland (Box 3)
    - Articles by ECB/Sweetland Faculty
    - Assessment
      - ACT Portfolio System 1994 (Box 3)
      - Assessment, Summer 1991 (Box 3)
      - Assessment Criteria 1988-1997 (Box 3)
      - Assessment Focus Groups 1995 (Box 3)
      - Assessment of Tutorial Students' Writing Portfolios 1987-1988 (Box 3)
      - Consequences of Changes in Assessment Standards 1989 (Box 3)
      - Costs of Portfolio Assessment 1993 (Box 3)
      - Development of the New Writing Assessment Instrument 1990 (Box 3)
      - Evaluating the ECB Portfolio Assessment Process 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - Portfolios 1987 (Box 3)
      - Portfolio Assessment Development 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Problems with a Portfolio Assessment 1998 (Box 3)
      - Report from the Stimuli Task Force 1987 (Box 3)
      - Report on Practicum in Transition to Self-Assessment circa 1999 (Box 3)
      - Self-Placement 2000-2002 (Box 3)
      - Task Force Report on the Use of Portfolios to Assess Students' Writing undated (Box 3)
      - Wayne Butler's Interchange 1993 (Box 3)
      - Writing Assessment Criteria 1988-1996 (Box 3)
      - Writing Assessment Research Reports 1987-1988 (Box 3)
      - Writing Portfolio 1994
    - Callaway Undergraduate Writing Prize 2000 (Box 3)
    - Center for Online Literacies: History, Mission and Goals 1994 (Box 3)
    - Change in ECB Activity Level 1993 (Box 3)
    - ECB Liaisons
      - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - Relationship between ECB and Composition 1983 (Box 3)
    - ECB Peer Tutoring Program 1990 (Box 3)
    - E-Notebook Implementation 1999 (Box 3)
    - "Extended Writing in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts Report on a Faculty Survey," 1987 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Survey 1978 (Box 3)
    - First Year Practicum Revision 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - First Year Seminar Program 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - High School Outreach
      - Academic Outreach 1996 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1997 (Box 3)
      - Dewey Center Writing Project 1988-1991 (Box 3)
      - MacKenzie High School 1999 (Box 3)
      - MacKenzie Oral History Project 2000-2001 (Box 3)
      - MacKenzie High School / University of Michigan Writing Program 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - Pioneer/University of Michigan Connection 1993 (Box 3)
      - Wade-McCree Scholars Program Proposal 1990 (Box 3)
      - Writing Across the Curriculum, Fall 1987 (Box 3)
      - "Writing Across the Millennium," 1999 (Box 3)
      - "Writing Across the Millennium," 2000 (Box 3)
    - LSA Minutes Concerning ECB 1978-1998 (Box 3)
    - Mellon Grant 1980-1986 (Box 3)
    - Political Science Department Pilot of Advanced Writing in the Disciplines 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Project -- U-M Instructional Environment and Online Writing Lab 1996 (Box 3)
    - Proposal -- Fellowships to Develop Thinking and Writing Courses 1987 (Box 3)
    - Relationship with Department of English 1984 (Box 4)
    - Report from Project on Writing and Writing Problems: Linguistics 211 (Box 4)
    - Report of the Ad-Hoc Committee on the First Year to the English Department Executive Committee February 1995 (Box 4)
    - Report on the ECB/Composition Relationship 1988 (Box 4)
    - Report on the Pilot for the Interdisciplinary Project, Fall 1995 (Box 4)
    - Report on the Residential College post-Freshman Year Seminar Practicum 2000 (Box 4)
    - Report of the Task Force Committee on Repeat Tutorial Arrangements 1987 (Box 4)
    - Report on Teaching Assistant Training and Development at the University of Michigan June 1995 (Box 4)
    - Seminar on Teaching: An Informal Report July 1995 (Box 4)
    - State of University Writing Level Complain Letters 1985 (Box 4)
    - Sweetland Multiliteracy Center 2001-2003 (Box 4)
    - U-M/Mackenzie Journalism Collaboration 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - University Writing Requirement
      - First-Year Writing Requirement 1998-2002 (Box 4)
      - Upper Level Writing Requirement 2000-2006 (Box 4)
      - Upper Level Writing Requirement Report 2012 (Box 4)
    - Writing Workshop 1994-1995 (Box 4)
- Publications and Printed Works
  The Publications and Printed Materials (1980-2008, 0.25 linear feet) series contains newsletters as well as writing-related instructional guides and pamphlets published by the Sweetland Center.
  - Argumentative Writing and Technical Terms 1989 (Box 4)
  - ECB Academic Writing Series: Using Computers as a Writing Tool circa 1980s (Box 4)
  - Gayle Morris Sweetland Writing Center Dedication November 19, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters
    - FForum, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - FForum, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
    - Gayle Morris Sweetland Writing Center Newsletter 1998-Fall 2008 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and Brochures (Box 4)
  - Teaching Introductory Composition, circa 1986 (Box 4)
  - The Junior/Senior Writing Course: A Manual for Faculty 1987 (Box 4)
- Audiovisual
  The Audiovisual series contains one undated videocassette of a faculty meeting and Christmas party.
  - VHS Videocassette, "Faculty Discussion of Normalization and Christmas Party," undated (Box 4)
- English Composition Board Writing Samples
  English Composition Board Writing Samples contain a selected assortment of writing samples from 1984 to 1989 intended for study and analysis by staff of the writing center. Because the essays are name identifiable, they are restricted for 75 years in accordance with the Student Records restriction.
  - 1984-1989 (Box 5)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 7, 2065 ]
  - 1984-1989 (Box 6)
  - 1984-1989 (Box 7)